<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <head>
        <title>Cinema and Memory</title>
        <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/css/interview.css" />
        <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/css/style.css" />
        <script type="text/javascript" src="/javascript/interview.js"></script>
    </head>
    <body><!--#include virtual="/inc/menuSSI.xhtml"-->
        <div id="boxes">
            <label for="person">Person</label>
            <input type="radio" id="person" name="selector" />
            <label for="title">Title</label>
            <input type="radio" id="title" name="selector" />
            <label for="genre">Genre</label>
            <input type="radio" id="genre" name="selector" />
            <label for="nationalCinema">National Cinema</label>
            <input type="radio" id="nationalCinema" name="selector" />
            <label for="place">Place</label>
            <input type="radio" id="place" name="selector" />
            <label for="epit">Epithet</label>
            <input type="radio" id="epit" name="selector" />
            <label for="persSing">Personal Singular</label>
            <input type="radio" id="persSing" name="selector" />
            <label for="persPlur">Personal Plural</label>
            <input type="radio" id="persPlur" name="selector" />
            <label for="possSing">Possessive Singular</label>
            <input type="radio" id="possSing" name="selector" />
            <label for="possPlur">Possessive Plural</label>
            <input type="radio" id="possPlur" name="selector" />
            <label for="collective">Collective</label>
            <input type="radio" id="collective" name="selector" />
            <label for="lex">Lexical Hesitation Marks</label>
            <input type="radio" id="lex" name="selector" />
            <label for="nonLex">Nonlexical Hesitation Marks</label>
            <input type="radio" id="nonLex" name="selector" />
        </div>
        <div id="rightPanel"></div>
        <div id="centerPanel">
            <h1>Interview with Viktoriia Sorkina</h1>
            <ul>
                <li>Interviewer: Maggie Burke</li>
                <li>
                    <a href="http://mtp.blogs.wm.edu">Russian Movie Theater Project (RMTP)</a>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <a href="https://www.wm.edu">College of William and Mary</a>
                </li>
                <li>Interview Date: July 2010</li>
                <li>Transcription and Translation Date: Fall 2010</li>
            </ul>
            <hr />
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p> This is a deed of gift for the transcript of the interview. If you sign this you
                will give us the right to use the interview in our research. This document also
                protects your rights in how we use your interview. </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>Yes </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p> We will be conducting an interview with you for a film project that is studying the
                social, political, and cultural history of Russia through film. We would like it if
                you could talk with us about your memories of going to the movies. We are especially
                interested in the details. In accordance with your answers we will write an essay,
                in which we will analyze the results of the questionnaire and write about the
                experience of going to the movies in Russia. The goal of this interview for us is to
                discover more about concrete people and the place of the movies in their lives.
                Thank you very much for your help and for your readiness to share your memories with
                us. This interview will be included for future listening on the film project’s
                website. If you’re not against it, let’s get started. </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p> Let’s. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p> For the project, please tell us your first name, patronymic, and last name, and the
                year you were born. </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p> My name is Victoria Mikhailovna Sorkina. <span class="persSing">I</span> was born in
                1975. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p> Thank you. Tell me about your first memories <span class="place">at the
                    movies</span>. </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p> Do you mean the <span class="place">movie theater</span> itself, or just the movies
                in general? </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p> Either. </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p> Either. (A black cat enters the room.) We don’t have any food. That’s interesting.
                Ok, a black cat. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p> Well, anything you’d like. The buildings or the films. </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p> My very first memories. <span class="persSing">I</span> think that<span
                    class="nonLex">...</span>my very first memories about the movies are connected
                of course with my childhood.
                <!-- "My" is not used in the Russian original.  Therefore not tagged in English. -->
                But as a child, when <span class="persSing">I</span> was really very little, <span
                    class="possSing">my</span> family wasn’t used to it, there wasn’t a tradition of
                going to the movies<span class="nonLex">...</span>and therefore <span class="persSing">I</span> usually watched cartoons at home. And in Russia
                there’s also that popular show <span class="title">“Good Night, Little
                Ones!”</span>, that is, the program that kids watch. And it’s still on even now,
                this show. And <span class="possSing">my</span> first memory about the movies, as you
                say, were of course <span class="genre">cartoons</span>. But what kinds were there
                earlier in Russia<span class="nonLex">...</span><span class="persPlur">we</span>
                didn’t watch <span class="nationalCinema">American</span>
                <span class="genre">cartoons</span> or any other kind. Therefore <span
                    class="persPlur">we</span> watched those typical <span class="nationalCinema"
                    >Soviet</span>, <span class="epit">really good</span>
                <span class="genre">cartoons</span>, which <span class="persSing">I</span> love even
                to this day. That is, they were my first memory. And then, then, for sure, the movie
                theater started already in my school-age years. That is, when<span class="persSing"
                    >I</span> was a student, <span class="possSing">my</span> parents took me to the
                movies, and we also went to the movies with school. Perhaps when<span
                    class="persSing">I</span> was on vacation with <span class="persSing">my</span>
                grandmother and grandfather, that is, in <span class="place">Sverdlovsk</span>, but
                now that city is called <span class="place">Ekaterinburg</span>. There was also a
                    <span class="place">movie theater</span> there. And<span class="persSing"
                    >I</span> went to see only <span class="genre">children’s films</span>. This
                    was <span class="possSing">my</span>
                <span class="lex">perhaps</span> first memory about the movies. And the first film
                    <span class="persSing">I</span> probably saw was <span class="title">A First
                    Grade Student</span>. Then it was really well known, and the book was also
                really well known. That’s what it’s called, <span class="title">A First Grade
                    Student</span>. And this was, let’s say, probably in<span class="possSing"
                    >my</span> first years at school. Then, maybe I’ve already said, then <span
                    class="persSing">I</span> remember already another such big impression from the
                movies, when <span class="persSing">I</span> went to the movie theater and saw the
                film <span class="title">Roman Holiday</span>. You’ve probably seen this movie too? </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>I haven’t seen it, but Iknow it. </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>Yes, with the <span class="epit">famous</span> and <span class="epit"
                    >magnificent</span>
                <span class="epit">Gregory Peck</span>, right? And <span class="epit">Audrey
                    Hepburn</span>. And this was a big impression on me, the big screen and a <span
                    class="epit">wonderful</span> film, right, which <span class="persSing">I</span>
                also saw on vacation. It was somehow fitting. That sounds about right. In school
                    <span class="persSing">I</span> didn’t go to the movies very often. But it’s
                possible this only strikes me because <span class="lex">maybe</span> the other
                children went more often. <span class="persSing">I</span> don’t know. What else? </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>Well, when did you go to the movies? Was it with your parents or your friends? </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>When <span class="persSing">I</span> was in school? Well of course<span
                    class="persSing">I</span> went with <span class="possSing">my</span> parents.
                There were also some sort of these school events, trips<span class="nonLex"
                    >...</span>trips to the movies with <span class="collective">everyone</span>
                from school together. But this<span class="nonLex">...</span> this <span
                    class="persSing">I</span> don’t remember very well. Then when <span
                    class="persSing">I</span> was already in high school, in the upper grades at
                school, when<span class="persSing">I</span> was almost finishing school, <span
                    class="persSing">I</span> went to the movies with<span class="possSing"
                    >my</span> friends. Yes. Well, it was probably just like that for everyone.
                    <span class="persSing">I</span> don’t know. <span class="persSing">I</span> also
                remember a really big impact from the film <span class="nonLex">...</span>
                <span class="title">Gone with the Wind</span>. Do you know that film or not? <span
                    class="title">Gone with the Wind</span>? <span class="title">Gone with the
                    Wind</span>? It was a really, really big impression. I’m sorry. It’s not
                important. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>Excellent! </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>(phone rings) Yes? Yes. Can <span class="persSing">I</span> call you back later? Yes.
                Sorry. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>Did you watch many Soviet movies or only cartoons? </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>As a child, as a child<span class="nonLex">...</span>I just watched <span
                    class="genre">cartoons</span>. Because <span class="colelctive">all</span> kids
                love ‘<span class="epit">kids films</span>,’ as we call them, <span class="genre"
                    >cartoons</span>. And there were also some sort of <span class="genre">kids
                    films</span>, <span class="epit">feature-length</span> ones. Yes, but what<span
                    class="persSing">I</span> watched as a child, these <span class="genre"
                    >children’s movies</span>, <span class="persSing">I</span> don’t remember them
                well. <span class="persSing">I</span> remember that<span class="persSing">I</span>
                saw the film The <span class="title">Adventures of Captain Grant</span> based on
                    <span class="title">Jules Verne</span>. Yes, that<span class="persSing">I</span>
                remember well. There was also something. Yes, right.<span class="persSing">I</span>
                cannot quite recall though what it was. Practically everything’s gone. Yes. <span
                    class="persSing">I</span> watched <span class="nationalCinema">Soviet
                    movies</span> too. But for these at any rate, <span class="persSing">I</span>
                think, <span class="persSing">I</span> didn’t go to the <span class="place">movie
                    theater</span>. <span class="persSing">I</span> saw them on television. But
                    <span class="persSing">I</span> know that, for example,<span class="possSing"
                    >my</span> parents often went to the movies. They watched those movies that came
                out every time. Yes, a new film. For example those movies by <span class="person"
                    >Eldar Ryazanov</span> and all other Soviet directors, who did something then,
                filmed something. But in order to watch <span class="nationalCinema">Soviet
                    films</span>
                <span class="persSing">I</span> don’t think<span class="persSing">I</span> went to
                the movies. In any case,<span class="persSing">I</span> don’t remember it. <span
                    class="persSing">I</span> remember when the movie <span class="title">Moscow
                    does not Believe in Tears</span> came out. <span class="persSing">I</span> was
                just a young girl. And <span class="possSing">my</span> parents went to the late
                showing of the film. When they came back, <span class="persSing">I</span> was really
                interested in what it was about. And <span class="possSing">my</span> mom told me the
                plot of the movie, just as well as she was able, because in general it’s hard for a
                little girl to understand what the movie’s about. As <span class="persSing">I</span>
                understood it, there was a prince, as <span class="possSing">my</span> mom explained
                to me then, and that the film’s about a princess. How a woman can become a princess.
                Right? Well, it was something like that. Later I watched that film when<span
                    class="persSing">I</span> was already a university student, <span
                    class="persSing">I</span> think. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>When you saw that film was it on television? </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>
                <span class="persSing">I</span> watched it on television, yes. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>Well then, do you remember the movie theater buildings? </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>The buildings? Of course <span class="persSing">I</span> remember the buildings.<span
                    class="persSing">I</span> don’t think that those <span class="place">movie
                    theaters</span> were really <span class="epit">comfortable</span>, like today.
                They were those <span class="epit">really typical</span> ones, all of them just like
                to others. But then <span class="persSing">I</span> didn’t think about that. <span
                    class="persSing">I</span> remember that then there was a tradition, when<span
                    class="persSing">I</span> went to the <span class="place">movie theater</span>
                <span class="persSing">I</span> always ate ice cream. Yes, in <span class="place"
                    >America</span> it’s popcorn, right? For example, now they also sell popcorn in
                the <span class="place">movie theater</span>. But<span class="persSing">I</span>
                remember, that then they sold ice cream. It was, as we say, part of the show. That
                is, a part of the whole experience. And it’s possible that for me, when <span
                    class="persSing">I</span> was young, it was actually even in general the main
                part. Because I don’t know what was more interesting, the ice cream or the movies.
                But in any case, of course, when you go and see the big screen, for you it’s like a
                miracle, magic. And in general you forget about everything.<span class="persSing"
                    >I</span> remember, that yes there is still another memory.<span
                    class="persSing">I</span> remembered, that <span class="">we</span> went to the
                movies once with school, once a month. It was a that subscription, <span
                    class="genre">children’s film</span>. <span class="persSing">I</span> really
                loved that. But what precisely we watched, <span class="persSing">I</span> remember
                that they were some sort of <span class="genre">fairy tales</span>. Maybe it was a
                film about <span class="title">Vasilisa the Wise</span>. Yes? Well anyway,<span
                    class="persSing">I</span> don’t remember. That is, then there was just the
                impression, that it was the movies. But for some reason no one film has stuck
                    in <span class="possSing">my</span> memory <span class="nonLex">...</span> from
                that time. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>In your youth, when you went to the movies with your friends and didn’t watch
                cartoons? What types of movies do you like? </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p><span class="lex">Well</span>, <span class="persSing">I</span> liked and still like
                    <span class="genre">dramas</span>, <span class="persSing">I</span> like a good
                    <span class="genre">romantic comedy</span>, <span class="persSing">I</span> like
                    <span class="genre">thrillers</span>. But for a <span class="genre"
                    >thriller</span>
                <span class="persSing">I</span> don’t go the movies.<span class="persSing">I</span>
                like <span class="genre">alternative cinema</span>. What is that? Well done <span
                    class="genre">art cinema</span> with an alterative outlook, with the director’s
                own outlook on things. There, just like that. That is in<span class="possSing"
                    >my</span> taste the films of <span class="person">Ingmar Bergman</span>, and
                    <span class="person">Woody Allen</span>, and something of the type, <span
                    class="persSing">I</span> don’t know, of that Forman, <span class="person">Milos
                    Forman</span>. Yes? That is<span class="persSing">I</span> like that <span
                    class="epit">classic</span>, <span class="epit">untraditional</span>, <span
                    class="epit">good</span> cinema.</p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>Woody Allen and Ingmar Bergman that’s foreign art cinema. Did you also watch Russian
                art cinema? </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>Do you mean some <span class="nationalCinema">Russian</span>
                <span class="genre">art cinema</span>? Yes, of course, naturally, of course I’ve
                seen it. Or do you have in mind that <span class="persSing">I</span> prefer to watch
                    <span class="nationalCinema">Russian cinema</span>? </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>Do you remember? </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>Of course. <span class="persSing">I</span> like <span class="person"
                >Tarkovsky</span>. <span class="lex">Well</span>, <span class="nonLex">...</span>
                and went to see him at the movies. And now <span class="persSing">I</span> also like
                to just watch <span class="person">Tarkovsky</span>’s films wherever, even on<span
                    class="possSing">my</span> own laptop. Yes? That is, what else from Russian
                classics? Now <span class="persSing">I</span> can’t say. <span class="lex"
                    >Probably</span> I’m more engrossed by <span class="nationalCinema">foreign
                    cinema</span>. But that’s me. <span class="lex">Maybe</span> other Russians
                would say something completely different. That is,<span class="persSing">I</span>
                prefer, <span class="lex">probably</span>, as it turned out, that<span
                    class="possSing">my</span> tastes congealed more around foreign directors. It
                seems that way to me. But there’s still one more name<span class="persSing">I</span>
                can’t at all remember. Maybe you can kindle <span class="possSing">my</span> memory –
                    <span class="title">The Taste of Pomegranate</span>.
                <!-- SYNTAX FOR ERRONEOUS, NEED TO CHANGE RELAX-NG, 
                    for CLASS WE NEED TO MAKE CHANGES in XML coding: @ana="circumlocution" or "misattribution"  -->
            </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>Pomegranate? </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>Yes. The <span class="title">Taste of Pomegranate</span>. </p>
            <!-- SYNTAX FOR ERRONEOUS, NEED TO CHANGE RELAX-NG, 
                for CLASS WE NEED TO MAKE CHANGES in XML coding: @ana="circumlocution" or "erroneouse reference"  -->
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>I don’t know. </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>It’s also a Russian director, but he, as we say, is of Armenian descent.
                <!-- SYNTAX FOR ERRONEOUS, NEED TO CHANGE RELAX-NG, 
                    for CLASS WE NEED TO MAKE CHANGES in XML coding: @ana="circumlocution" or "erroneouse reference"  -->If
                I remember I’ll tell you a bit later. Yeah<span class="nonLex">...</span>there’s no
                way, now way it’ll come to me. Of course <span class="persSing">I</span> love
                Fellini’s films, and everything, for example, written by <span class="person">Tonino
                    Guerra</span>. There, probably something like that.<span class="persSing"
                    >I</span> also like <span class="nationalCinema">Chinese cinema</span>. Now,
                this last time the very famous director <span class="title">Wong Kar-wai</span>
                almost mesmerized me. And I’ve seen almost everything that he’s done. And that’s how
                it is. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>And now, have you seen international art films like at Cannes, or festivals? </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>I follow them. <span class="persSing">I</span> follow the festivals, and let’s say,
                those they invite there. And once not long ago <span class="persSing">I</span> saw
                how the <span class="place">festival in Cannes</span> was, and a director from <span
                    class="place">Vietnam</span> won there. And it was the first time for <span
                    class="place">Vietnam</span>, and the film is called <span class="title">Uncle
                    Boonmee</span>. There’s a long name for the film. It seems it’s something like
                    <span class="title">Uncle Boonmee and who he was in a Previous Life</span>.
                Something like that. <span class="persSing">I</span> don’t exactly remember the
                title. But of course <span class="persSing">I</span> really wanted to see this film,
                but it still hasn’t gone into Russian distribution. Let’s say. Also, of course<span
                    class="persSing">I</span> follow the festival in <span class="place"
                    >Berlin</span>, at <span class="place">Cannes</span>,<span class="persSing"
                    >I</span> often watch the Oscar ceremonies. And<span class="persSing">I</span>
                remember, that last time at Cannes, <span class="persSing">I</span> think <span
                    class="person">Pedro Almodovar</span> won. Well,<span class="persSing">I</span>
                don’t remember exactly. The time before<span class="nonLex">...</span>yes, <span
                    class="persSing">I</span> think it was the time before. I’m also interested in
                what happens, what the outcomes are at the <span class="place">Moscow
                    festivals</span>, but <span class="persSing">I</span> can’t say that now <span
                    class="nationalCinema">Russian cinema</span> is very successful. One can name
                very few directors, whom they would actually like to see. That’s how it is. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>Do you know in St. Petersburg or, maybe, do you know movie theaters in which they, in
                which one can see international art films? </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>Actually international films about art, right? Yes, there are, do you have in mind
                art, like something, that there is, wasn’t let’s say like a <span class="genre"
                    >blockbuster</span>, right? </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>Not a blockbuster, like... </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>That is cinema like <span class="genre">art cinema</span>. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>Yes. </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>
                <span class="persSing">I</span> think that there aren’t any <span class="place"
                    >movie theaters</span> of precisely this kind. It does happen, that a film is
                playing, a film is showing in the theaters. For example, a director’s entire corpus.
                Yes, for example, in a <span class="place">movie theater</span> of <span
                    class="collective"><span class="possPlur">ours</span></span> all of <span
                    class="person">Ingmar Bergman</span> is showing, yes, the whole month. Yes. Of
                course, there’s also that <span class="place">movie theater</span>, the <span
                    class="place">Dom Kino</span>. At the <span class="place">Dom Kino</span> the
                classics are often showing. One can always watch something good. There are also
                festivals around the city. For example, the <span class="nationalCinema">Polish
                    film</span> festival, <span class="nationalCinema">Japanese film</span>
                festival, <span class="nationalCinema">American</span> and so on. Or just a showing
                of a certain director. And there, yes, probably at the <span class="place">Dom
                    Kino</span> in <span class="place">St. Petersburg</span>, most often of all
                you’ll see something <span class="epit">serious</span>. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>Did you like to go to the festival? </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>I go often, yes. <span class="persSing">I</span> happens that<span class="persSing"
                    >I</span> go and often even watch some sort of classic, but it also happens that
                    <span class="persSing">I</span> watch something new. There, there it’s somehow
                like that. But when <span class="possSing">my</span> friends really say to me, that
                there’s a good film and it’s worth seeing it, then<span class="persSing">I</span> go
                too. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>How else would you watch new films, if you didn’t want to watch blockbusters or
                popular films? </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>How else, what do <span class="persSing">I</span> usually watch? </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>Yes. </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>Well, when it concerns blockbusters? Yes, that<span class="nonLex">...</span>I very
                rarely watch them. But if I watch, that’s most of all over the internet. Yes. And
                probably more than any other way. As far as this <span class="epit">serious</span>
                cinema is concerned, like <span class="persSing">I</span> already said
                    generally<span class="persSing">I</span> go to the <span class="place">movie
                    theaters</span>. Or again <span class="persSing">I</span> watch something at
                home. That’s more often, of course, at home. But also at the <span class="place"
                    >movie theater</span>. But for <span class="genre">blockbusters</span>
                <span class="persSing">I</span> really don’t go. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>Now you didn’t go to the movie theater because you don’t like new films or movie
                theaters as they are now, or is it something else? </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>It’s hard to say. <span class="persSing">I</span> go, but not very often, probably
                because there just isn’t time. Generally, you remember, that you can watch a given
                film at home and in general you’re lazy to get up and go. Generally<span
                    class="nonLex">...</span>generally it’s like that, that you go and you can take
                some sort of little piece of your time and devote it anyway to going to the movie
                theater. <span class="persSing">I</span> think that because of that now it’s more
                comfortable to watch everything at home. There’s no time for going there. But it
                happens that <span class="persSing">I</span> do go. Yes, that is,<span
                    class="persSing">I</span> would probably say, possibly, 50% or 70% of the time
                    <span class="persSing">I</span> watch at home and the remaining 30%<span
                    class="persSing">I</span> watch at the movie theater.<span class="persSing"
                    >I</span> go to the movie theater, when it’s that sort of mood and when<span
                    class="persSing">I</span> know that there’s a film that<span class="persSing"
                    >I</span> would really like to watch on the big screen, let’s say. Because there
                are films that are just hard to watch on the little screen. For example, there was
                that, <span class="persSing">I</span> think two or three years ago, was that film
                out <span class="title">The Island</span>. The well made movie, <span class="title"
                    >The Island</span>, maybe you’ve heard about it. With <span class="person">Peter
                    Mamonov</span>. There, and <span class="persSing">I</span> went to the movies.
                Because it’s not always good to watch a movie on television or over the internet,
                for some you need a big screen for it. That’s from these considerations. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>Do you think, that you prefer to watch the same genres now as<span class="nonLex"
                    >...</span>
            </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>Just the same. <span class="persSing">I</span> think that there’s a tendency in that,
                    <span class="persSing">I</span> think. Well, of course as a child you watch
                everything that interests you, and it interests you with what it ends. That is
                you’re interested in the ending. Therefore you can watch <span class="genre"
                    >adventure films</span> – you’re always interested in a <span class="genre"
                    >fairy tale</span>. When young maybe <span class="persSing">I</span> watched
                    <span class="genre">romantic films</span> more often. Like <span
                    class="colelctive">all</span> young girls, right? Who love romantic stories. But
                now that I’m already, let’s say, in <span class="possSing">my</span> grown-up
                    years,<span class="persSing">I</span> watch more for the quality of the film.
                And the director is even more important to me, rather than that. That is it’s
                important to me how it’s done. Of course genre, of course, one might even say not
                genre, but rather say simply that it’s for the topic of the movie. Let’s say, it’s
                more about how the film speaks to me. But it seems to me, that the great directors,
                they always explore, talk about the timeless. About timeless themes, timeless
                questions for which they don’t have answers. And since, most of all it’s generally
                never important what genre it’s made as. But it is important how it’s done, and
                about what, let’s say, and that’s that. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>Do you like directors more than genres? </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>Than genres, of course. <span class="persSing">I</span> select a director regardless
                of the genre because it might be a really good genre, but the film turns out to be
                completely uninteresting. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>But what films don’t you like? </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>Actively don’t like, actively? </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>Yes </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>I don’t like movies that are made for, how to say<span class="nonLex">...</span>the
                general audience of people. Movies that<span class="nonLex">...</span>when the
                director plays with the audience. And when we know that they’ll be here everyone
                cries, and when they’ll be here everyone laughs. And this<span class="persSing"
                    >I</span> don’t like, because the last time <span class="person"
                    >Mikhalkov</span> works on this, let’s say, on these tropes<span class="nonLex"
                    >...</span>such patterns, right? That means they use this trope. And<span
                    class="persSing">I</span> don’t like this, when everything is all, let’s say,
                painfully mundane. Yes, and when it’s all made for the <span class="colelctive"
                    >general populace</span>, for the common people and so on, that is, <span
                    class="persSing">I</span> don’t like that right now, the popular Russian theme,
                let’s say, of who we are, that is what sort of people <span class="collective"
                    >all</span> Russians are, right? That is,<span class="persSing">I</span> don’t
                like these techniques. And yes, there<span class="persSing">I</span> don’t like
                films that are made for everyone, let’s say. <span class="persSing">I</span> don’t
                like movies where you don’t have to think. And in general, where you know that here
                you have to cry a little and here you have to laugh a little. And overall, it just
                doesn’t interest me. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>Well, okay, have you seen new movies, like Burnt by the Sun 2 or Admiral? New Russian
                films? </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>I saw <span class="title">Admiral</span>, but <span class="persSing">I</span> didn’t
                see <span class="title">Burnt by the Sun 2</span> because it didn’t interest me,
                what <span class="person">Mikhalkov</span> did, because<span class="persSing"
                    >I</span> know that it’s not <span class="epit">high art</span> cinema,<span
                    class="persSing">I</span> know, that earlier <span class="person"
                    >Mikhalkov</span> made <span class="epit">outstanding</span> films, he’s an
                outstanding actor, and a very good director, but now it’s not so simple, and he’s
                completely concentrated on this Russian Orthodox idea, and it’s all very rough.
                There, and <span class="persSing">I</span> don’t like <span class="epit">these
                    tendentious, false</span> films. There it apropos of<span class="nonLex"
                    >...</span>apropos of <span class="person">Mikhalkov</span>. Apropos of <span
                    class="title">The Admiral</span>, <span class="persSing">I</span> saw it, but in
                general <span class="persSing">I</span> also think that it’s completely done, let’s
                say, like black and white, somehow completely for <span class="collective">the
                    masses</span>. <span class="persSing">I</span> think that it isn’t Kolchak’s
                story. <span class="persSing">I</span> think that it has practically nothing in
                common with what happened then. Because it’s like so, and the tendency, earlier old
                films were against the whites, against the white guards, right? For the reds. Now
                they’re making films against the reds, right? Against the communists, for the white
                guards, right? <span class="lex">Well</span>, in any case it’s all very narrow. And
                you can never confine it into some sort of formula. Kolchak was too complex of a
                person for such a simplistic film. Besides, the film deals with lives of female
                characters and for me it looked ridiculous how the film handled that aspect of the
                plot. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>And what do you think about the difference between new movies like The Admiral and
                old movies, like Moscow Does Not Believe in Tears or The Irony of Fate. </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p><span class="lex">Well</span>, the entire thing is in the director, let’s say, since
                because <span class="title">The Irony of Fate</span> was made by <span
                    class="person">Vladimir Menshov</span>, it seems to me that it’s an <span
                    class="epit">excellent</span> film and made very well. And the entire matter, on
                the first level, is in the screenplay, and secondly, in the actors, and of course in
                the entire story. And it seems to me that <span class="genre">Moscow Does Not
                    Believe in Tears</span> is an <span class="epit">excellent</span>
                <span class="epit">Soviet</span> film, where, in general it’s half <span
                    class="genre">comedy</span>, sure, and half <span class="genre">drama</span>,
                    <span class="persSing">I</span> don’t really know but in any case, there’s no
                kitchiness there, and <span class="persSing">I</span> would say that. And in general
                in <span class="nationalCinema">Soviet cinema</span>, in <span class="epit"
                    >good</span>
                <span class="nationalCinema">Soviet cinema</span>, it was different from this, and
                it’s possible, yes possible, that now it seems a little funny, but it seems to me
                that even now, if some, even a foreigner were to see this cinema, that they would
                like it because these were films <span class="epit">of high quality</span>. Good
                directors who are able to deliver now and were able to then too. As far as new
                cinema is concerned now, it has in general no relation at all to good artistic
                cinema. Unfortunately. That’s <span class="possSing">my</span> opinion, because now
                everything is done quickly, in order to please, let’s say, <span class="nonLex"
                    >...</span> it’s necessary that it be film <span class="epit">in favor of the
                    government</span>, in order to please first of all the government, there, and
                this tendency is outlined by this very <span class="epit">strange</span>, <span
                    class="epit">simplistic</span> cinema, which anyone in general can understand.
                Right? And in general<span class="persSing">I</span> don’t think that, how to say,
                that this is cinema on which<span class="persSing">I</span> need to spend time <span
                    class="nonLex">...</span> to see. Although now there’s also good cinema,
                probably, but possibly not in this large scope, like it was before, but really it
                can’t be like that, since there just weren’t good directors. That is, there is
                something, but mostly, let’s say, in small portions. <span class="lex"
                    >Probably</span> because there exists the tendency, that cinema always exists,
                just like any form of art, it’s just like some sort of flow, right, and ebb, like
                when sometime there was that period in Italy, right, of good cinema, when <span
                    class="person">Antonioni</span>, <span class="person">Fellini</span>, etc. were
                working. Today when watching <span class="nationalCinema">Italian cinema</span>
                there’s practically nothing <span class="epit">interesting</span>. And it’s just the
                same in <span class="place">Russia</span>, there was such a time, now, <span
                    class="lex">probably</span>, we’re on a break. That’s what <span
                    class="persSing">I</span> think. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>Well,I think that that’s everything I can ask, but do you have something you would
                like to ask me, or something you’d like to say? </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>Ask, yes, <span class="persSing">I</span> would like to ask whether there exists now
                in America <span class="genre">alternative cinema</span>, for example, like you’re
                thinking of? </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>I often watch alternative movies, in America, <span class="persSing">I</span> know
                that we have those kind of directors, who make movies for the festivals, like <span
                    class="place">Cannes</span>, or <span class="place">Sundance</span>, but <span
                    class="persSing">I</span> rarely watch these movies<span class="nonLex"
                    >...</span>
            </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>What do you like? </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>I don’t remember something, but <span class="persSing">I</span> think, that that
                aspect of culture in America is called “Indie,” it’s alternative culture, which now
                exists as popular and new movies like <span class="title">Juno</span>. That was two
                or three years ago. It’s a really popular movie, but anyway, <span class="persSing"
                    >I</span> don’t know how to say this in Russian, but it (shows) aspects from
                this culture. </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>Understood. <span class="persSing">I</span> would also like to ask, what do Americans
                like from our movies? </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>I think that, unfortunately, it’s really just <span class="genre"
                >blockbusters</span>, like <span class="nationalCinema">American movies</span>,
                which in Russia, it’s like big <span class="nationalCinema">American movies</span>
                    and<span class="nonLex">...</span>
            </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>No, no, <span class="persSing">I</span> would like to know, what do Americans like in
                    <span class="nationalCinema">Russian cinema</span>? </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>In <span class="nationalCinema">Russian cinema</span>! Sure, it’s rare that Americans
                watched <span class="nationalCinema">Russian cinema</span> before 1990 and then,
                    <span class="persSing">I</span> think that if<span class="nonLex">...</span>if
                someone already knows something about Russia, they might watch <span class="person"
                    >Mikhalkov</span>’s films, or old movies like <span class="title">Moscow Does
                    Not Believe in Tears</span> or <span class="title">Irony of Fate</span>
                    would<span class="nonLex">...</span> would be more rare than <span class="title"
                    >Moscow Does Not Believe in Tears</span>, but <span class="persSing">I</span>
                think that many Americans have never seen <span class="nationalCinema">Russian
                    movies</span>. </p>
            <h3>Sorkina: </h3>
            <p>Yes, certainly, but it’s really hard to find Russian who’ve not seen <span
                    class="nationalCinema">American movies</span>, because with <span
                    class="possPlur">us</span> now <span class="nationalCinema">American
                    cinema</span> has such a draw, <span class="persSing">I</span> would say, of the
                    <span class="epit">American</span>
                <span class="title">blockbuster</span> in Probably because in Russia now they are
                making so few movies. They’re only making a few new Russian films, and it’s these
                that are shown over and over again on television. <span class="lex">Well</span>
                anyway, <span class="lex">most likely</span> something like that. </p>
            <h3>Burke: </h3>
            <p>Well, you know <span class="persSing">I</span> think that directors like <span
                    class="person">Mikhalkov</span> want to make <span class="nationalCinema"
                    >Russian films</span> like <span class="epit">American</span>
                <span class="genre">blockbusters</span>. </p>
        </div>
    </body>
</html>
