<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title> Interview with voronin: electronic version </title>
                <author>
                    <name ref="voronin">MIKHAIL VORONIN</name>
                </author>
                <editor role="interviewer">
                    <name ref="parks">JESSICA PARKS</name>
                </editor>
                <editor role="interviewer">
                    <name ref="clark">EMILIE CLARK</name>
                </editor>
                <editor role="transcriber">
                    <name ref="clark">EMILIE CLARK</name>
                </editor>
                <editor role="transcriber">
                    <name ref="kitchen">HANNAH KITCHEN</name>
                </editor>
                <editor role="translator">
                    <name ref="clark">EMILIE CLARK</name>
                </editor>
                <editor role="translator">
                    <name ref="kitchen">HANNAH KITCHEN</name>
                </editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name ref="nitz">ANDREW NITZ</name>
                    <name ref="prokhorova">ELENA PROKHOROVA</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>College of William and Mary</publisher>
                <authority> Russian Movie Theater Project <bloc> The Russian Movie Theater Project
                        is an archive and a study of film exhibition in St. Petersburg during the
                        twentieth century: a portrait of film exhibition and movie-going scene in
                        Soviet Leningrad and Post-Soviet St. Petersburg. The project is inspired by
                        Williamsburg Theater Project (led by Professor Arthur Knight) and the
                        international initiative, the History of Moviegoing, Exhibition, and
                        Reception (HOMER) Project. While many Western cinematic traditions are
                        represented in the HOMER project, there is no online archive covering
                        Russian cinema. The RMTP aims to fill that gap. Most histories of Russian
                        and Soviet cinema operate under the assumption that all films released were
                        available to all citizens of Russia Soviet Union. When the films received a
                        limited release for political reasons, researchers provide anecdotal
                        evidence about how these films were distributed. The Russian Movie Theater
                        Project would like to create an empirical portrait of Russians’ movie going
                        habits and film exhibition patterns at different periods of Soviet and
                        Russian history. For example, when and where Soviets were able to see
                        Western films in Stalinist Russia? How did the availability of Italian,
                        Indian, and American films changed after Stalin’s death? How does Soviet-era
                        propaganda and post-Soviet promotion affect film distribution and film
                        attendance? Using computational tools, this Project examines oral history
                        interviews, in which interviewees reconstruct their moviegoing experiences
                        in St. Petersburg, Russia. To see the computational module of the project
                        click here. Specifically, the Project analyzes what moviegoers remember
                        (films, actors, directors), how they evaluate films, actors, characters, how
                        they define themsleves as narrators (I or we), what they hesitate about when
                        they recollect their moviegoing experiences, and how their cinematic
                        experiences shape their identities as Soviets, Russians, and global
                        citizens. </bloc>
                </authority>
                <pubPlace>Williamsburg, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <date type="interview">July 2013</date>
                <date type="translation">Fall 2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <p> EDITORIAL POLICY
                        <!--
We follow TEI Guidelines "16.2.1 Pointing Elsewhere."
-->
                    </p>
                    <p> The project is approved by Protection of Human Subjects Committee (PHSC) of
                        the College of William and Mary. <ref
                            target="http://www.wm.edu/offices/sponsoredprograms/researchcompliance/guidanceandprocedures/"
                        />
                    </p>
                    <licence> Distributed via permission from interviewee (given in the Deed of Gift
                        to the College of William and Mary) </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <!--
Information about the source of the interview: an audio or video recording.
-->
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>INTERVIEW WITH MIKHAIL VORONIN</title>
                        <author>
                            <name ref="voronin">MIKHAIL VORONIN</name>
                        </author>
                        <editor role="interviewer">
                            <name ref="parks">JESSICA PARKS</name>
                        </editor>
                        <editor role="interviewer">
                            <name ref="clark">EMILIE CLARK</name>
                        </editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>College of William and Mary</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Williamsburg, VA</pubPlace>
                        <date>4 July, 2008</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note> The interview with Liudmila Danilenko is part of the Russian Movie
                            Theater Project, which examines history of moviegoing expereinces in the
                            USSR and Russia. Michael Roberts has conducted the interview on 4 July,
                            2008 in St. Petersburg, Russia. </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p> The interview with Mikhail Voronin is part of the Russian Movie Theater Project,
                    which examines history of moviegoing expereinces in the USSR and Russia. Jessica
                    Parks and Emilie Clark conducted the interview on 4 July, 2008 in St.
                    Petersburg, Russia. </p>
            </abstract>
            <creation>BACKGROUND OF INTERVIEW</creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="ru">RUSSIAN</language>
            </langUsage>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="interviewer">
                    <persName ref="roberts">MICHAEL ROBERTS</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="interviewer">
                    <persName ref="parks">JESSICA PARKS</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="interviewer">
                    <persName ref="clark">EMILIE CLARK</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="interviewee">
                    <persName ref="voronin">MIKHAIL VORONIN</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <u xml:id="sp1" who="parks">Today is the 29th of July, 2013. We’re in Saint Petersburg,
                Russia. My name is Jessica Parks, and my colleague is Emily Clark. Emilay and I are
                conducting an interview with Mikhail Voronin. We’re conducting an interview with you
                for a film project that analyzes the general, political, and cultural history of
                Russia through film. We would like for you to tell us about your memories of going
                to the movies and we’re particularly interested in the details. On the basis of your
                answers we will write an essay, in which we will analyze the results of the
                questionnaire and write about moviegoing in Russia. The goal of this interview for
                us is to learn as much as we are able about individual people and the place of the
                movies in their lives. Thank you very much for your readiness do share your memories
                with us and also for helping us. This interview will be added for listening on the
                film project’s website. If you’re not against it, then let’s begin.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp2" who="voronin">Very good!</u>
            <u xml:id="sp3" who="parks">Tell us, where and when were you born?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp4" who="voronin">I was born in <rs type="place" key="urals">the Urals</rs>,
                in the city of <rs type="place" key="ufa">Ufa</rs>. It’s one of the cities with a
                million or more people, a sufficiently large city in <rs type="place" key="russia"
                    >Russia</rs>. I spent the first fifteen years of my life there.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp5" who="parks">Where did your mom and dad work?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp6" who="voronin">My parents divorced when I was still a child. My mom
                worked as a stewardess, flew, in general around <rs type="place" key="russia"
                    >Russia</rs>. Sometimes close by abroad.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp7" who="parks">What sort of education do you have?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp8" who="voronin">Now I have a university degree. I finished the War College
                this year.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp9" who="parks">What cities have you lived in?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp10" who="voronin">I lived in <rs type="place" key="ufa">Ufa</rs>, the
                capital of the <rs type="place" key="republicBashkirtostan">Republic of
                    Bashkirtostan</rs>. I also lived in <rs type="place" key="moscow">Moscow</rs>
                for three years, in the capital of <rs type="place" key="russia">Russia</rs>, and
                the last six I’ve lived in <rs type="place" key="stPetersburg">Saint
                Petersburg</rs>, the <rs type="epit" key="stPetersburg">prettiest</rs> city in my
                view.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp11" who="parks">Do you remember the first time you went to the movies?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp12" who="voronin">No, I don’t remember the first time. Poorly, I remember
                it poorly.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp13" who="parks">What kinds of movies did you watch?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp14" who="voronin">Just as I started to go to the movies from childhood,
                everything was in chronological order. Starting with <rs type="title"
                    key="rockyBullwinkle">Rocky and Bullwinkel</rs>, maybe you know, and ending with
                    <rs type="genre" key="horror">horror movies</rs>, <rs type="genre" key="comedy"
                    >comedies</rs>. Now, in principal, now I only rarely go to the movies.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp15" who="parks">How old were you?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp16" who="voronin">I don’t remember, probably, it was first grade, seven
                years old. Seven or eight.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp17" who="parks">Who did you go to the movies with?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp18" who="voronin">Who didn’t I go to the movies with! Who did I go with the
                first time? In general? I went to the movies with my mom, teacher, with almost all
                my girlfriends. I loved to go to the movies with friends, with a big group. Yes, in
                a big group and then after we’d loosened up a bit. I would, well, I can’t say this
                on the record what they usually loosen up with before going to the movies. Your
                people will understand.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp19" who="parks">How much did a ticket cost?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp20" who="voronin">A ticket cost, I don’t remember, a couple copecks. At the
                beginning…at the beginning when we were kids and had very little money of our own in
                our pockets, we went to the morning screenings, then it was cheaper. And afterwards
                at anytime. A ticket cost from, from one dollar, in your system, up to ten or twenty
                dollars.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp21" who="parks">What was the name of the movie theater. Describe the
                theater.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp22" who="voronin">The movie theater was called <rs type="place"
                    key="kinoteatrIskra">Iskra</rs>. It designed at first in the Soviet style, in
                the old style. “Old School.” But then they renovated it, they did a great job, and
                now it’s a <rs type="epit" key="kinoteatrIskra">modern</rs> screening room, a whole
                lot of people go there, cinema is strangely popular in <rs type="place" key="russia"
                    >Russia</rs> recently, and all the premieres are there, and all the stars go
                there, for example.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp23" who="parks">Did you walk or take transport?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp24" who="voronin">Normally I drove, it was far enough from home, the
                nearest <rs type="place" key="movieTheater">movie theater</rs> from my house was
                twenty kilometers away.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp25" who="parks">How did you get there?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp26" who="voronin">Normally, at the beginning we took the bus, and later,
                when we were already grown up, we drove.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp27" who="parks">Did you have one or more movie theaters near home?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp28" who="voronin">No, near home there weren’t any <rs type="place"
                    key="movieTheater">movie theaters</rs>. We exchanged VHS tapes, those old ones.
                But the movie theater was far from home. There were some theaters in the city, five
                of them at first. But now ten of them, I think.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp29" who="parks">Compare the movie theaters.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp30" who="voronin">It’s a bit hard to compare them, because they’re all
                typical, similar to one another, all the <rs type="place" key="movieTheater">movie
                    theaters</rs>. But there is a difference, in that...the <rs type="place"
                    key="movieTheater">movie theater</rs> could be a freestanding building or in a
                shopping complex. But, as a rule, now all the <rs type="place" key="movieTheater"
                    >movie theaters</rs> we have are in shopping complexes.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp31" who="parks">When did you start going to the movies alone?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp32" who="voronin">I don’t remember how old, about 10.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp33" who="parks">Did you like going to the movies, and why?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp34" who="voronin">I only liked going to the movies for <rs type="genre"
                    key="blockbuster">specific films</rs>. I go only rarely just for that reason.
                Only for specific blockbusters, or some sort of well known premieres. Of well known
                directors or actors. My friends and I preferred to go out, to play soccer or
                hockey.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp35" who="parks">How often did you go to the movies? To which showings? The
                morning ones, afternoons, evenings?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp36" who="voronin">Yes, to different ones. When we wanted, then we went. As
                children we went to the morning ones, and then when we grew up, it’s cold in <rs
                    type="place" key="russia">Russia</rs> and in order not to freeze we went to the
                movies.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp37" who="parks">Going to the movies, was it a special occurrence or a
                regular one?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp38" who="voronin">As a child maybe it was something special, but now, to go
                to the movies…we think that going to the movies is better than doing something. If
                you have nothing better to do, you know, right, no better way to spend your time,
                you can go to the movies.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp39" who="parks">How did going to the movies change when you grew up or
                finished school?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp40" who="voronin">Well it became less interesting, less captivating. They
                simply started being downloaded on the internet.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp41" who="parks">What were your favorite genres as a child?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp42" who="voronin"><rs type="place" key="russia">Comedy</rs>, from early
                childhood, is my favorite genre, <rs type="place" key="russia">comedy</rs>, I also
                liked <rs type="genre" key="action">war movies</rs>, and now I prefer some sort of
                    <rs type="genre" key="melodrama">melodramas</rs>, or ones based on real
                events.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp43" who="parks">What were your favorite genres when you were in
                college?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp44" who="voronin"><rs type="genre" key="adult">Porno</rs>, of course. Of
                course <rs type="genre" key="adult">porno</rs>, it's true you don’t need to change
                anything, it’s that way for all Russian students. And then <rs type="genre"
                    key="action">war movies</rs> and <rs type="genre" key="comedy"
                >comedies</rs>.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp45" who="parks">Do you have a favorite movie?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp46" who="voronin">Yes, I think I have a few favorite movies. I’ve simply
                watched a lot of movies, the last movie, that left an impression is called <rs
                    type="title" key="mavericks">Mavericks</rs>…or <rs type="title" key="mavericks"
                    >Укротители волн 1</rs> in Russian. It’s a bad translation, with <rs
                    type="person" key="butler">Gerald Butler</rs>. “Maybe,” but maybe you know it.
                Why did I like it? It’s based on true events.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp47" who="parks">Did you have favorite actors or actresses in from foreign
                cinema? Who and why?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp48" who="voronin">Yes. Sure favorite actors. Why? Why, I don’t know. <rs
                    type="person" key="theron">Charlize Theron</rs>, for example. Yes, <rs
                    type="person" key="theron">Charlize Theron</rs>, and, well <rs type="person"
                    key="depp">Johnny Depp</rs>, he’s good, particularly in <rs type="title"
                    key="piratesCaribbean">Pirates</rs>. Secondly, maybe <rs type="person"
                    key="carrey">Jim Carrey</rs>, yes, <rs type="person" key="carrey">Jim
                    Carrey</rs>. Particularly in <rs type="title" key="mask">The Mask</rs> and <rs
                    type="title" key="aceVentura">Ace Ventura</rs>, the best of his work. <rs
                    type="person" key="murphy">Murphy, Eddie Murphy’s</rs> a smart alec. But he also
                did stuff.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp49" who="parks">Do you remember any movie or outing to the movies
                particularly? Talk about that visit.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp50" who="voronin">No. I don’t remember specific outings to the <rs
                    type="place" key="movieTheater">movies</rs> in particular. I remember movies
                better, which you remember your whole life. The <rs type="title" key="godfather"
                    >Godfather</rs>, “Godfather.” And also a Russian serial, maybe you’ve seen it,
                    <rs type="title" key="brigade">The Brigade</rs>. The Russian serial <rs
                    type="title" key="brigade">Brigade</rs>, and the Russian movie <rs type="title"
                    key="brother">Brother</rs> and <rs type="title" key="brother2">Brother 2</rs>.
                “Brother and Brother 2.” Well, yes, I think there’s a few more movies, but yes, <rs
                    type="title" key="lifeIsBeautiful">Life is Beautiful</rs>. “It’s a Beautiful
                Life.” The Italian movie. Maybe I messed up the tile. The Italian movie. Many of the
                films watched with my friends come highly recommended by Internet Movie Data
                Base.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp51" who="parks">How did you spend your free time apart from going to the
                movies?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp52" who="voronin">Went out, played soccer and hockey. I think very
                typically, just like all teenagers, who have free time and who are able to buy
                something forbidden for themselves.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp53" who="parks">Who did you normally go to the movies with?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp54" who="voronin">Normally either with guys or with girls. We go very
                rarely in a mixed group. As a rule, it’s either only boys or girls. “Only boys or
                only girls.”</u>
            <u xml:id="sp55" who="parks">More men or women?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp56" who="voronin">Who go to the movies? Oh I don’t know, probably more
                women But most likely since we have more women in general.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp57" who="parks">In general, did people go to the movies more often with
                family or with friends or girlfriends?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp58" who="voronin">Yes, no more girls go to the movies, because it gives
                them something to do. There, families go rarely, on the weekends, families go to the
                movies.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp59" who="parks">Were there lines in the <rs type="place" key="movieTheater"
                    >movie theaters</rs>? Do you remember waiting in line?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp60" who="voronin">Yes, but very rarely. There were very rarely lines. Five
                minutes maximum.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp61" who="parks">Did different groups sit in different parts of the movie
                theater?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp62" who="voronin">Different groups? Well, when, how. In different places,
                there were, there weren’t places, some there were, <rs type="pron"
                    subtype="persPlur">we</rs> were able to lay down there and watch.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp63" who="parks">Did people make noise, or were they quiet during the
                showing?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp64" who="voronin">Ah, not always. That is while watching some showing, <rs
                    type="pron" subtype="persPlur">we</rs> would make noise.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp65" who="parks">How did people dress for the movies? Atypically or like
                normal?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp66" who="voronin">In different ways. For many going to the movies, it’s a
                special event. Particularly for girls looking to show off, and <rs type="pron"
                    subtype="persSing">I</rs> don’t know how, they’re able to dress in stockings,
                thin ones, to wear high heels, it’s not comfortable, it’s stupid, but in order to be
                especially good looking. The guys dressed normally.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp67" who="parks">Did you know people who worked at the movie theater?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp68" who="voronin">Yes, I know a couple. And as it was they could go for
                free.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp69" who="parks">What was the atmosphere like in the theater?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp70" who="voronin">It depends. At <rs type="genre" key="horror">horror
                    movies</rs> it’s usually <rs type="epit" key="kino">fun</rs>, because <rs
                    type="pron" subtype="persPlur">we</rs> go to <rs type="genre" key="horror"
                    >horror movies</rs> with our girlfriends and at the most grueling moment, we
                scare them but good. <span type="lex">Well</span>, just to laugh.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp71" who="parks">Describe the movie theater, and if possible, compare it
                with movie theaters today.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp72" who="voronin">I really don’t know how to describe it. There’s a big
                screen there, it’s dark and loud.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp73" who="parks">Describe the sounds and smells that you remember when you
                think about the movie theaters.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp74" who="voronin">The smell of popcorn. <rs type="pron" subtype="persSing"
                    >I</rs> think sound, a <rs type="epit" key="kino">strong growing sound</rs>.
                With a strong base.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp75" who="parks">Were the chairs comfortable?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp76" who="voronin">Then how, usually yes, <rs type="epit" key="kino">usually
                    comfortable</rs>.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp77" who="parks">Was it cold at the movies, warm, hot, stuffy?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp78" who="voronin">That also depends, sometimes the air conditioning didn’t
                work, and sometimes it worked too well.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp79" who="parks">Was the movie theater big? How many screening rooms were
                there?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp80" who="voronin">When, it was<span type="nonlex"/>There were from two to
                fifteen screening rooms, <rs type="pron" subtype="persSing">I</rs> think that sounds
                right. But individual seats from 50 to 300. Up to 300 individual seats, they were
                different.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp81" who="parks">Was the theater only for movies, or for other events
                too?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp82" who="voronin">Sometimes for other events, but generally only for
                movies.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp83" who="parks">Was there a snack bar? What did they sell at the snack
                bar?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp84" who="voronin">They always sold popcorn, Pepsi, and soda at the
                snackbars, and beer too. And there was something to eat. Ice cream. “Ice cream.”</u>
            <u xml:id="sp85" who="parks">Were there ticket collectors in the theater and how old
                were they usually?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp86" who="voronin">Well there were always ticket collectors, generally it
                was young people. Generally it was young girls, up to thirty.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp87" who="parks">Where did you usually like to sit and why?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp88" who="voronin">That depends on who you go to the movies with. With
                friends we normally sat in the middle, in order to see better, but with girls
                normally off to the side. Places for kissing.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp89" who="parks">Were the movies silent or talkies? Black and white or
                color?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp90" who="voronin">They were always color, always had sound, with the
                exception of special films, not special ones, but when it was the desire of the
                director. If in all the <rs type="place" key="movieTheater">movie theaters</rs> of
                the world it black and white and silent ones cropped up, then <rs type="pron"
                    subtype="possPlur">we had</rs> it too. But all the others were color, with
                sound.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp91" who="parks">What was the quality?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp92" who="voronin">The quality was excellent. And many <rs type="place"
                    key="movieTheater">theaters</rs> now are in 3D, IMAX format. <rs type="pron"
                    subtype="persSing">I’m</rs> just not a huge fan of recent cinema, I’m only there
                rarely, there’s no time.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp93" who="parks">Which movies were the most popular among viewers and
                why?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp94" who="voronin">Among viewers, the most popular films were, <rs
                    type="pron" subtype="persSing">I</rs> think<span type="nonlex"/> those that were
                advertised well. Russians have this habit, to go to popular, cheesy movies, if the
                advertising is good, then a lot of people go to the movies. If they like the movie,
                then they tell friends, and their friends go. And <rs type="pron" subtype="persSing"
                    >I</rs> think, almost all the movies, and that are popular in America, are also
                popular in America. How it generally is in the world, it’s decided by ratings.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp95" who="parks">Did the often show foreign films in the movie theaters?
                Films from which countries?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp96" who="voronin">They’re almost always foreign films, because after the
                collapse of the <rs type="place" key="sovietUnion">Soviet Union</rs>
                <rs type="pron" subtype="possPlur">we</rs> didn’t make many movies. There, but now,
                they show both <rs type="nationalCinema" key="foreignCinema">foreign movies</rs> and
                    <rs type="pron" subtype="possPlur">ours</rs>, from all countries, from
                absolutely all counties, but in general, of course, it’s <rs type="nationalCinema"
                    key="americanCinema">American movies</rs>, in general, because they’re <rs
                    type="epit" key="americanCinema">the most abundant</rs>. <rs type="epit"
                    key="americanCinema">Most easy</rs> to get ahold of.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp97" who="parks">Which movies did you like most of all?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp98" who="voronin">Most of all, I liked, “well,” while I was growing up, as
                a child <rs type="genre" key="skazka">fairy tale movies</rs>, and then <rs
                    type="genre" key="action">war movies</rs>, and then more <rs type="genre"
                    key="melodrama">melodramas</rs>. Depends. As I feel like. That’s it.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp99" who="parks">Were there movies that children couldn’t go to and why?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp100" who="voronin">Yes, there were quite a lot of those kinds of movies,
                and now they’re restricted. Why? It’s important to everyone why. Because they
                contain scenes for adults. With the R rating, <rs type="nationalCinema"
                    key="americanCinema">your American one</rs>, but the kids go in general. If they
                want.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp101" who="parks">Your parents didn’t let you go or the movie theater
                management?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp102" who="voronin">They didn’t let us, but <rs type="pron"
                    subtype="persPlur">we</rs> went anyway. And the <rs type="place"
                    key="movieTheater">theater</rs> management didn’t prohibit us when <rs
                    type="pron" subtype="persSing">I</rs> was young, and now <rs type="pron"
                    subtype="persSing">I</rs> don’t now, <span type="lex">maybe, maybe</span> now
                they prohibit it.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp103" who="parks">Did you try to go to a movie that you weren’t allowed to
                go to?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp104" who="voronin">Of course. And there, there was interest.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp105" who="parks">Talk about it, how it was.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp106" who="voronin">It was easy because, <span type="lex">well</span>, in <rs type="place" key="russia">Russia</rs>, when <rs type="pron" subtype="persSing">I</rs> was little,
                they didn’t pay especial attention to age and didn’t follow the rules especially.
                Yes, and now, the main thing is to earn money. And it’s not important if a kid a few
                years younger goes into a movie for adults. The kid himself wants that.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp107" who="parks">Do you remember any film that had problems coming to the
                screen? Talk about that film.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp108" who="voronin">To be honest, <rs type="pron" subtype="persSing">I</rs> don’t remember, because I wasn’t
                interested. If there had been problems, it simply wouldn’t have come to the screen,
                and no one would have seen it. Therefore <rs type="pron" subtype="persSing">I</rs> don’t remember these movies.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp109" who="parks">How did you find out about the theater’s schedule of
                screenings?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp110" who="voronin">About the <rs type="place" key="movieTheater">theaters’</rs> schedules? I found out either by
                advertising, by advertisement banners in the streets and on signs, or on the
                internet, on the <rs type="place" key="movieTheater">theaters’</rs> schedule. Or from friends, who had like some movie.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp111" who="parks">Did you read about movies in magazines or in the
                papers?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp112" who="voronin">Yes, but by accident, if it cropped up by accident. In
                Playboy, for example.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp113" who="parks">How did movie advertising change from the Soviet
                times?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp114" who="voronin">Hardly at all, the advertising just got better and
                better looking. It got bigger.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp115" who="parks">Did your parents go to the movies?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp116" who="voronin">Of course they went, my parents only went to the
                movies.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp117" who="parks">What did they watch?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp118" who="voronin"><rs type="pron" subtype="persSing">I</rs> don’t know, they didn’t talk about it much, <rs type="pron" subtype="persSing">I</rs> think
                the same thing, but earlier almost all <rs type="place" key="movieTheater">movie theaters</rs> showed only Soviet movies.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp119" who="parks">They went to the movies together with you, with one
                another, alone?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp120" who="voronin">Well then, it depends. Either together and without me,
                that is, it didn’t depend on anything, on their mood, per their desire.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp121" who="parks">Did you have a television set?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp122" who="voronin">Yes.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp123" who="parks">When you bought it, did you go to the movies more or
                less?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp124" who="voronin">Just the same.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp125" who="parks">Do you know when talkies first came out?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp126" who="voronin">No, I don’t know, I don’t remember, but long ago. Long
                ago, <span type="nonlex"/>after, <span type="nonlex"/> somewhere, the first sound films existed before the Second World War, I
                think, in <rs type="place" key="america">America</rs>. And after the Second World War we already had them in the
                <rs type="place" key="sovietUnion">USSR</rs>.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp127" who="parks">Do you remember movies from during the war? After the war?
                During Perestroika?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp128" who="voronin">Yes, <rs type="pron" subtype="persSing">I</rs> saw them, naturally, a bit later. <rs type="pron" subtype="persSing">I</rs> went to the
                premieres. I wasn’t that busy. There, but then I saw a lot of movies, yes, they’re
                interesting enough. They all have their own style, that is, despite that there were
                many censored films, which the Soviet government prohibited to be shown and only now
                have they come to the screen. But, to be honest, I don’t really care for them.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp129" who="parks">How did your going to the movies change with time and
                why?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp130" who="voronin">I rarely want to because there’s little time, and <rs type="place" key="movieTheater">the
                movies</rs> have already gotten old. Earlier it was something amazing and rare, <span type="lex">maybe</span>.
                Rarely, when you go only a little, does it capture your sprit. And now I feel like
                something new. Some kind of new enjoyments, but <rs type="pron" subtype="persSing">I</rs> know many people, many of <rs type="pron" subtype="possSing">my</rs>
                friends, who are in the habit of going to the movies, they just don’t know where
                else to go. For them it’s enough to go to the movies.</u>
            <u xml:id="sp131" who="parks">Would you like to add anything in conclusion?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp132" who="voronin">In conclusion <rs type="pron" subtype="persSing">I</rs> want to add<span type="nonlex"/>that I have to go to the
                movies somehow. <rs type="pron" subtype="persSing">I</rs> haven’t been there in a while, and for <rs type="title" key="ironman3">Ironman 3</rs>, “<rs type="title" key="ironman3">Ironman 3</rs>, very
                good.”</u>
            <u xml:id="sp133" who="parks">Do you have a suggestion for us regarding what theme to
                ask about in an interview in the future?</u>
            <u xml:id="sp133" who="voronin">Yes, just not <rs type="pron" subtype="possSing">with me</rs>!  With someone else.  Because <rs type="pron" subtype="persSing">I</rs> can only say very little</u>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
